Inventory of the John C. Ridlon Papers, 1846-1936 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John C. Ridlon Papers, 1846-1936 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library, Duke University
Ridlon, John C., 1852-1936.
4.1 Linear Feet Approx. 3250 Items
Physician and surgeon specializing in orthopedic medicine practicing in Chicago, Illinois.
Collection consists of both loose and bound manuscripts as well as correspondence, photographs, and illustrations relating to John Ridlon's extensive research and writings on orthopedics. Bound volumes comprise: six casebooks (1889-1892); four letterbooks (1873-1903); an autograph manuscript, Some comments on the principles and practice of Hugh Owen Thomas (undated); a scrapbook of figures and illustrations (undated); three volumes composed of reprint clippings and manuscript notes (undated); and a bound volume of reprints (1888-1923). Also included are 85 additional reprints dating from 1888 to 1935, photographs and illustrations of orthopedic deformities and treatments, and fourteen diplomas from various educational institutions. Correspondents include: R. Osgood, A. Steindler, P. D. Wilson, R. K. Ghormley, J. E. Goldthwait, A. B. Judson, R. W. Lovett, H. W. Orr, S. W. Mitchell, and H. Cushing. Letters also document Ridlon's involvement with two charitable institutions: the Home for Destitute Crippled Children and the Country Home for Convalescent Children. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
Individuals using this collection are reminded that personally-identifiable medical information is subject to privacy laws.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John C. Ridlon Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library from the Medical Center Library in 2011.
Biographical Note
John C. Ridlon (1852-1936) was a physician and surgeon specializing in orthopedic medicine practicing in Chicago, Illinois.
Collection Overview
This material, which documents Ridlon's life and work, consists of both loose and bound manuscripts as well as correspondence, photographs, and illustrations relating to Ridlon's writings on orthopedics. Bound volumes comprise: six casebooks (1889-1892); four letterbooks (1873-1903); an autograph manuscript, Some comments on the principles and practice of Hugh Owen Thomas (undated); a scrapbook of figures and illustrations (undated); three volumes composed of reprint clippings and manuscript notes (undated); and a bound volume of reprints (1888-1923). Also included are 85 additional reprints dating from 1888 to 1935, photographs and illustrations of orthopedic deformities and treatments, and fourteen diplomas from various educational institutions. Correspondents include: R. Osgood, A. Steindler, P. D. Wilson, R. K. Ghormley, J. E. Goldthwait, A. B. Judson, R. W. Lovett, H. W. Orr, S. W. Mitchell, H. Cushing. Letters also document Ridlon's involvement with two charitable institutions: the Home for Destitute Crippled Children and the Country Home for Convalescent Children.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Ridlon, John, 1852-1936.
Osgood, Robert Bayley, 1873-1956.
Steindler, Arthur, b. 1878.
Wilson, Philip (Philip Duncan), b. 1886.
Ghormley, Ralph K. (Ralph Kalb), 1893-1959
Goldthwait, Joel Ernest, b. 1866.
Judson, Adoniram Brown, 1837-1916.
Lovett, Robert W. (Robert Williamson), 1859-1924.
Orr, H. Winnett (Hiram Winnett), 1877-1956.
Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914.
Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939.
Lorenz, Adolf, 1854-1946.
Orthopedics--United States--History.
Orthopedic surgery--United States--History.
Orthopedists--Correspondence.
Ankylosing spondylitis.
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Casebooks Series, 1889-1892, (2 boxes)
  Bound holograph manuscripts containing case notes on orthopedic patients with a variety of complaints, including descriptions of each case and often personal details of patients such as the date the case began, name, age, sex, address, diagnosis, and treatment for each case. Includes several one-page manuscripts laid in as well as outlines made of patient body parts showing measurements of the actual curvature and size of affected areas.
  - Vol. 1, 1889, Aug.-1891, Aug. (Box 11)
  - Vol. 2, 1889-1892 (Box 11)
  - Vol. 3, 1890, Jan.-Sept. (Box 11)
  - Vol. 4, 1890, Sept.-1891, May (Box 11)
  - Vol. 5, 1891, May-Dec. (Box 12)
  - Vol. 6, 1891-1892 (Box 12)
- Correspondence Series, 1873-1936, (10 boxes)
  Contains correspondence, as well as a few account sheets, contracts, meeting minutes, deeds, loan agreements, bylaws, printed material, bills and receipts, reports, some photographs, reprints, clippings, and typed manuscripts. Correspondents include: R. Osgood, A. Steindler, P. D. Wilson, R. K. Ghormley, J. E. Goldthwait, A. B. Judson, R. W. Lovett, H. W. Orr, S. W. Mitchell, H. Cushing. Letters also document Ridlon's involvement with two charitable institutions: the Home for Destitute Crippled Children and the Country Home for Convalescent Children.
  - Correspondence, A-B (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, C-E (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, F-H (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, H-K (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, L-M (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, M-P (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, Q-T (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, U-Z (Box 8)
  - Letterbooks, 1873-1880, 1895, (2 vols.) (Box 14)
    Bound correspondence written in both typed and holograph scripts containing transcriptions correspondence concerning financial matters, professional concerns, by John Ridlon to various correspondents.
  - Letterbooks, 1895-1896, 1896-1903, (2 vols.) (Box 15)
- Medical Images Series, 1888-1904 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Contains photographs and proofs of images and illustrations relating to Ridlon's writings on orthopedics.
  - A Collection of Orthopedic Illustrations (Box 8)
  - Photographs: (Box 8)
    - Spinal deformities and treatments, undated (Box 8)
    - Congenital dislocations of the hip paper, 1888-1904, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - Pseudo hypertrophied paralysis and curves, undated (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook of figures and illustrations, circa 1900, (24 cm. 70 leaves) (Box 16)
    Bound scrapbook containing illustrations of braces and other tools for treating patients with orthopedic complaints, diagrams illustrating the use of these tools, and photographs and drawings of affected persons. Images were probably used in Ridlon's published writings.
- Writings Series, circa 1900 and undated, (3 boxes)
  - Some Comments on the Principles and Practice of Hugh Owen Thomas, by John Ridlon, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    Handwritten manuscript (on the reverse of Principles and Practice of Orthopaedic Surgery, by Philip Lewin). Hugh Owen Thomas was a Welsh surgeon considered the father of orthopaedic surgery in Britain. Typed versions of the manuscript can be found in the Correspondence Series.
  - Club-foot, circa 1900, (10 cm. 22 leaves) (Box 12)
    Bound typescript manuscript. Pages of text are mounted on to the manuscript, which is an essay by J.R. on the congenital disorder talipes, vernacularly known as clubfoot, including illustrations of presentations of the disorder, possible treatments, and photographs of patients with the disorder printed in the text.
  - General Principles, circa 1900, (10 cm. 31 leaves) (Box 12)
    Bound typescript manuscript with holograph notes containing writings on the general practice of orthopedics as well as diagnosis and treatment of spondylitis and scoliosis.
  - Spondylitis, circa 1900, (10 cm. 72 p) (Box 12)
    Bound notebook written in holograph script containing writings and collected research on cases of spondylitis including causes and cures, as well as clippings pasted in, illustrated notes laid in showing spinal curvature of patients with J.R.'s notes, and two photographs of a dissection of a patient with the disorder. Includes multiple pages of both holograph and typescript notes laid in.
  - Reprints: Collected Papers of Dr. John Ridlon, Orthopedic Surgery, 1888-1923, (1 vol.) (Box 13)
- Oversize Materials, 1846-1924, (1 folder)
  A variety of diplomas from educational institutions.
  - Diplomas, 1846-1924, (14 items) (Opaperfolder 1)